The eyes of the world are on Paris and France.
So how better than for us to contribute a series on what is probably, Dominic,
I mean, one of the great seismic events, not just in European, but in global history.
Certainly one of the two or three greatest stories in world history.
I mean, the rollercoaster of bloodshed, violence, utopianism, insurrection, excitement, you name it.
So this is the kickoff for our first series, which will take us through the first couple of years of the revolution.
Yeah, so we can look at some of the causes, some of the background to the revolution,
and then we'll take through the storming of the Bastille and go up to the point where the king, Louis XVI,
and his queen, Marie Antoinette, who we've just been hearing about, try to get out of France.
And spoiler alert, they fail.
And that is the cliffhanger on which we will leave it.
Yeah, because, of course, everybody knows.
What will then happen to the king and queen?
Yes.
And I think Marie Antoinette is a kind of wonderful focus for looking at some of the causes,
because she's very, very celebrated.
I mean, one of the instantly kind of recognisable figures.
She must be one of the two or three most well-known people in all French history, I would have said.
Yes.
And at the time, she is seen by enthusiasts for the revolution as the absolute embodiment of everything that prompted it.
You know, she is the kind of the incarnation of Ancien Régime, arrogance, of aristocratic splendour,
and of a kind of quality of vampirism that has leached the French people of what should be rightfully theirs.
And in her lifetime, before and then particularly after the revolution,
she is the object of absolutely kind of obsessive hatred.
And it's also a kind of prurient hatred, you know, because it is tied up with kind of fantasies.
About what she's been getting up to.
And I guess that that, I mean, that runs through to the present day,
because the one phrase that everyone would associate with her,
let them eat cake, is still repeated, isn't it?
Despite the fact that she never said it.
I know.
And the phrase, the original phrase is qu'ils mangent de la brioche.
So let them eat brioche has slightly different connotations, doesn't it?
Yeah, because I always kind of imagine them, you know, a big gato, strawberries on the top or something.
But she never said it anyway, so there's no point in dissecting it, I guess.
To some degree, other than the fact that the fact that people think she said it is indicative of this idea of her and Louis,
who's supposedly kind of both, who's her puppet,
then living this life of unbelievable depravity and licentiousness and arrogance and not caring.
All of which, well, not all of it is completely wrong, but there are definitely huge problems with that.
Nuances there.
But again, I mean, against that, against the image of Marie Antoinette,
as a kind of depraved vampire, there's also been right from the beginning for conservatives,
a sense that she is, you know, she is the archetype of the victims of the revolution.
Her fate exemplifies what critics of the revolution see as its destructiveness, as its kind of bloodlust.
So the revolution itself is cast as a vampire.
And in England, the person who classically first articulates that is the Irish politician and Whig,
so not even a Tory, Edmund Burke, who November 1790 wrote reflections on the revolution in France.
And in that, he famously recalls seeing Marie Antoinette kind of 16 or 17 years before at the court,
glittering like the morning star full of life and splendor and joy.
And he famously enthuses,
I thought 10,000 swords must have leaped from their scabbards to avenge even a look that threatened her with insult.
But the age of chivalry is gone.
That of sophisters, economists and calculators has succeeded.
And the glory of Europe is extinguished forever.
I would say his is the, among biographers and among people who studied the revolution,
it's his take actually that is more enduring than the,
than the let them eat cake, she's a vampire school of thought, isn't it?
Because actually now it's, I would say most writers are filled with horror
when they look at what happened to Marie Antoinette,
this young girl who arrived in France and was turned into a hate figure for the mob.
Chantal Thomas, who we opened with,
I mean, her book is about the vituperation that is kind of lashed on Marie Antoinette.
And she has a section where she talks about how biographers through the 19th and into the 20th century,
there was a debate about whether these were true or not.
And she just says, you know, none of these stories about the incest and the vampirism are true.
I mean, they're obviously not true.
And she says that most recent biographies have been written,
and to quote her, with sympathy, if not with love.
And I would say that's probably true of her as well,
because she wrote a novel that then got turned into a film called Farewell My Queen in English
that featured Diane Kruger.
So Helen of Troy and Troy.
As Marie Antoinette.
And that's a French film.
But of course, Marie Antoinette has also been a kind of an American pinup.
So a film that was massively popular with my daughters when they were growing up,
came out in 2006, is Sofia Coppola's Marie Antoinette,
in which she's kind of cast as, you know, very much a contemporary heroine.
She's surrounded by her squad.
She's got converse trainers in the cabinet.
You know, she rushes around Versailles to new wave bands.
And what was interesting about that,
I was kind of reading up about the reception of it in France,
because it was premiered at Cannes.
And there it was greeted with boos and then with cheers.
So kind of answering boos and cheers by the French journalists who'd been watching it,
which I guess kind of sums up a massive division in France itself.
Because Marie Antoinette stands for the revolution to some degree,
because what you think of Marie Antoinette,
you know, you ask a French, an educated Frenchman,
what they think of Marie Antoinette,
and their answer will tell you, well, they think of the revolution probably,
and probably also where they stand politically even today in the 21st century,
don't you think?
Yeah, I really, I mean, I do.
And I think to a degree that may be true as well in the broader world,
perhaps a bit.
I mean, it's much more focused in France, obviously.
And I think that that sense of ambivalence,
you know, is Marie Antoinette a monster or is she a victim?
Is she someone to be detested and loathed?
Or is she someone to be pitied and admired?
That's an ambivalence that is there even before the revolution.
So what is the way that she is viewed by the French public
is a kind of mixture of loathing and desire.
Because she's not always hated.
That's an important point to make.
No, she's not.
And there are certain, you know, she's very popular with certain segments of society.
And I think that
she's cast either as a kind of emblem of royal grace,
because she's, as we will see, in a way, she's a very, very modern figure.
Yeah, completely.
She kind of basically, I think, invents the French ideal of fashion.
She's way ahead of the game.
But to other people, this makes her the kind of the embodiment of frivolity or decadence.
She's a very proactive queen.
Queens in France generally are not expected to play a proactive role in court life
and national life, still less national life.
Marie Antoinette comes to do that.
And she's a kind of emblem of all the paradoxes that we'll be talking about
in the context of the revolution.
But she is, the fact that she's a figure of fantasy is really crucial
because not just her, but the revolution itself is about the creation of stories,
the projection of stories and narratives onto facts of the economy, agriculture,
the crowds, the court, everything.
It's how you structure the story that basically determines your attitudes to the revolution, I think.
Do you think that's...
I absolutely, yeah, totally agree, Tom.
I mean, historians like Simon Sharma and Robert Danton have written brilliant books
about how the French Revolution is there.
It's a sort of hall of mirrors or a hall of narratives, I suppose.
Very appropriate for Versailles.
For Versailles, exactly.
So let's start not at Versailles, but with Marie Antoinette herself.
So she is born.
She was born, Tom, in 1755.
And of course, the single most important thing about her, I would say,
is that she is not French.
She is Austrian.
She is...
We love the Habsburgs on The Rest Is History.
I don't think there'll ever be a historical podcast in the history of mankind
that is so keen on the Habsburgs as The Rest Is History.
We've had Edward Habsburg talking about the Habsburgs.
We've had Franz Ferdinand, great friend of The Rest Is History.
And now another Habsburg, Marie Antoinette.
Yes, although she's born Maria Antonia.
And I think that it's fair to say that her identity as an Austrian
and as a Habsburg is kind of fundamental both to how her admirers see her
and how her detractors see her.
So to her admirers, she is an embodiment of a new age of peace
between what traditionally have been the great rivals in European politics.
Yeah.
And it's interesting that, you know,
in the late 19th century, Charles V and François I,
you know, these are the people who are kind of tearing Europe up
while Luther is busy getting on with his stuff.
And France and the Habsburg Empire have been the great geopolitical rivals
on the continent of Europe.
But this has changed over the course of the 18th century
due to the emergence of two new great powers.
Yeah.
One of those is Britain, very happy to say.
So in the Seven Years' War, Britain is taking on France
and winning as a kind of global power.
But on the continent, there's the emergence of Prussia.
Yes.
And Prussia is hungry for a lot of Austria's traditional territories.
And under its great king, Frederick II,
it annexes a province called Silesia, doesn't it?
Which is basically now, it's a chunk of Poland.
Yeah.
And the Habsburgs are terribly upset about this.
And basically, they kind of enter into an alliance with France
so that they can get Silesia back.
And France enters into an alliance with Austria
so that she can have a counterweight to Britain.
So the diplomatic revolution historians call this,
because it's such a seismic moment in European history.
Yeah.
So the Seven Years' War breaks out in 1756
with Britain and Prussia against Austria and France.
And the following year, a very heavyweight figure in French politics,
the Duc de Choiseul,
arrives in Vienna as the French ambassador.
And the rulers who greet him, they're a couple, aren't they?
So the emperor is Francis I.
But the person who's really kind of cracking the whip
is his wife, the empress, Maria Theresa.
And she is a very, very proficient politician.
Indeed, one might say stateswoman.
But she's also very, very fertile.
And the Habsburgs have always, I mean,
it's been their boast, isn't it,
that some empires get their way by fighting.
We do it by marrying off our children.
And Maria Antonia is their 11th daughter
and, as it will turn out, their last daughter.
And the reason that the Duc de Choiseul is interested in her
is that she is one year younger
than the grandson of Louis XV, the French king,
also inevitably called Louis.
And his very fertile mind is thinking,
well, we could, you know,
we could maybe marry them off.
A brilliant way to cement the alliance
and to ensure that the alliance endures.
Yes.
And so in due course,
Choiseul goes back from Vienna.
He goes back to Paris
and he becomes the foreign minister,
basically the kind of the,
almost the prime minister for Louis XV.
And he's kind of pushing this idea.
He's saying, you know,
we should really try and cement this alliance.
And it comes into further focus in 1765
when Louis XV's son
and therefore the father of this guy who,
this Louis,
who is being lined up to marry Maria Antonia,
he dies.
And so the grandson of Louis XV
is now the Dauphin,
the kind of French equivalent of the Prince of Wales,
the heir to the throne.
He's 11.
So he's 11 and Maria Antonia is then what?
Sorry, is she 10?
10, yeah.
On the 4th of April, 1770,
it's all agreed.
The marriage contract is signed.
There's a kind of weird thing
where they do a proxy marriage in Vienna.
So the new emperor,
Maria Theresa's son, Joseph,
he stands in for the Dauphin.
And then two days later,
Maria Antonia is put into a carriage
along with 56 other carriages
and they set off from Vienna to go to France.
And people who are enthusiasts for this alliance
think this is brilliant.
Absolutely wonderful.
But of course in France,
there are lots of people who are not enthusiasts,
because as you said,
I mean,
these are,
these are ancestral enemies.
They have,
of course,
come together under the pressure
of Prussia and Britain.
But culturally,
imaginatively,
the idea of Austria
to most French men and women
is basically this horrendous place,
our enemies.
The Austrians can't be trusted.
And that baggage,
she is never able to shed it
for the rest of her life.
So right the way through her career
and kind of to an escalating degree,
she is always referred to as Le Trichienne.
So the Austrian,
but if you put the emphasis on Chien,
that's bitch.
Yeah,
in France.
So it's the kind of the ostrich bitch.
So she's always being portrayed either as an ostrich
or as a dog or both.
And the weird thing is,
is that this isn't actually remotely fair
because her father is basically French.
So,
so Francis,
the first,
he's the Duke of Lorraine.
He is a French Royal descent.
And there's a case for saying that
Marie Antoinette is actually one of the most French Queens
that the Bourbon,
the Royal dynasty have ever had,
because normally they're marrying queen,
foreign Queens who have no French connections at all.
But what's interesting is that,
you know,
her father basically gets written out of the story
and she is portrayed as being her mother's daughter,
solely her mother's daughter.
Maria Theresa is seen as this terrifying Virago
who is out to destroy France.
And so,
Marie Antoinette is cast as a kind of Trojan horse
who's been sent into the,
you know,
the very stronghold of French power
to destroy it from inside.
In Simon Sharma's words,
the spy whore,
he calls it,
he says,
that's the image that is,
I mean,
we're jumping ahead,
but that's the image that people later have of her.
And Maria Antoinette,
who becomes,
I mean,
she really does become Marie Antoinette.
So actually French has been her first language.
She speaks it initially with a German accent,
but that very rapidly,
you know,
she very rapidly loses that.
And in preparation for her life at the French court,
she's had a French tutor called the Abbe de Vermont,
who turns up and is appalled to discover that
Marie Antoinette has no,
basically she hasn't had any education at all.
And throughout her life,
she's,
she has no interest in books.
She's incredibly,
kind of not,
not remotely.
Although she is interested in,
in kind of the cultural temperature,
isn't she?
She's,
as we will see,
she's very into kind of,
but I think she kind of absorbs it with,
I mean,
it's said of her that no one has ever seen her finish a book.
And I think that that is kind of widely believed.
And he complains of a quality that will be repeatedly applied to her,
which is her,
her frivolity,
her lightness,
the fact that she,
she is not a heavy person.
I think it would be fair to say,
but he also acknowledges that,
you know,
she has,
she has great charm.
She has great poise.
She is also,
she's not conventionally pretty because she has,
um,
the kind of,
you know,
the classic protuberant lower lip of a Habsburg.
Yeah.
But she,
you know,
she has,
the Abbe says a perfect porcelain complexion.
She has brilliant blue eyes.
She has a very sweet oval face.
So basically,
you know,
she will do.
Yeah.
Well,
that's the,
the reports,
Robert Danson in his book,
uh,
the revolutionary temper,
um,
says that when the pamphleteers newspapers and whatnot,
we're talking about her in France,
they all said,
she's actually very nice looking,
you know,
she's blonde hair,
beautiful,
pale complexion.
Everyone is pleased.
She looks like a queen.
She does.
And she,
and,
and as we will see,
she,
um,
she becomes a great icon of beauty and fashion and style.
Um,
and there's a kind of symbolic moment where she ceases to be Austrian and becomes French,
which is,
um,
she,
you know,
she's traveling up from Vienna with her,
in her 57 carriages.
And on the 7th of May,
1770,
they reach,
um,
the Rhine and there's an island in the middle of it.
And this wooden pavilion has been,
uh,
built that looks like a kind of,
you know,
a perfectly tiny Chateau.
And it has five rooms inside it.
Um,
and there's kind of two on the Austrian side,
two on the French side,
and there's a kind of room in the middle.
And Marie Antoinette goes into the Austrian rooms.
She's divested of her clothes,
down to her kind of underwear.
She's then put into a French ceremonial dress.
She's led into the central drawing room.
The door leading into the French rooms is opened.
Um,
she looks back,
the doors,
the Austrian doors have been shut.
And,
um,
all the Austrian servants have,
have vanished.
And,
um,
Marie Antoinette is handed over to this terrifying woman,
who is the maitresse d'etiquette,
the woman who is going to instruct her in the ritual of,
of the court,
um,
called the Comtesse de Neuilly.
What was that noise?
Comtesse de Neuilly.
Neuilly.
Yeah,
it's just too many vowels.
There's basically four vowels in that.
It's a scrabble.
Yeah,
it is.
It's a scrabble heaven.
And,
Marie Antoinette bursts into tears at the sight of this terrifying woman.
Flings herself into,
into the Comtesse's arms.
The Comtesse,
massively embarrassed,
very stiff,
shrugs her off,
performs a low curtsy.
Marie Antoinette apologizes,
um,
and says,
pardon me.
These are for the family in the fatherland I'm leaving.
For the future,
I shall not forget that I am French.
And the Comtesse de Neuilly says,
yeah,
you better not.
I'm here to,
to whip you into shape.
So,
off they go.
And Tom,
just one thing.
Yeah.
She is 14 years old.
She's not yet 15.
Yeah.
So,
I mean,
this is a,
imagine what an unbelievably terrifying moment this must be for her.
And what makes it even worse,
she has a adorable little dog who she has to leave behind,
but we'll come to that later.
It's a crucial part of the story.
Anyway,
on they,
on they rattle.
And,
um,
it,
it takes them a week to,
uh,
to meet with the Dauphin and the French King.
And they do it outside the forest of Compiègne.
The Dauphin and the,
the Dauphine,
as,
as Marie Antoinette now is,
um,
are introduced.
Three days later,
they are married and she is now the queen of France.
Just on the marriage,
Tom,
um,
one bad omen,
one very dark omen.
If you know,
anyone knows about Russian history,
they will,
they will spot the,
uh,
resemblance.
Um,
Nicholas the second,
Alexandra,
when they were crowned,
there was a massive,
uh,
stampede afterwards and hundreds of people were killed.
Well,
after the,
after the marriage of,
uh,
the Dauphin and Marie Antoinette,
there was another stampede.
There's a fireworks display that goes horribly wrong.
Perhaps 150 people were killed in the crush.
And so after that,
whenever people
Doesn't a firework kind of drop onto a tent?
Right,
exactly.
Exactly.
There's a,
there were two rival,
they've got two rival fireworks designers,
uh,
a man called Monsieur Torre and a guy called Ruggeri.
And Ruggeri goes second.
So he wants to outdo the other bloke.
It's a,
it's an incredibly elaborate fireworks display.
It goes wrong.
A firework falls onto this temple that he's built,
a temple of Hymen.
And in the crush,
150 people,
50 people are killed.
And so whenever people remember,
they'd look back later on,
they say doomed from the start.
What a bad omen.
We should never have got involved with this Austrian woman.
You know,
the fireworks were a warning.
And there's kind of great emblem,
isn't there?
Kind of of,
uh,
the arms of France and the arms of the Habsburgs.
Yeah.
Uh,
kind of intertwined.
And the fact that it has generated this disaster,
as you say,
is seen as an omen.
And I think that that reflects the fact that the French don't only hate the Austrians,
but kind of look down on them because Austria relative to France has been declined.
Since the 16th century.
And France now is with the exception of Russia.
Um,
it's by far the largest kind of European realm.
So it's been described in the 18th century.
It's been described as the China of Europe.
You know,
it has by far the largest population 28 million twice as big as Britain.
So and Britain,
even with Ireland,
um,
this,
and it has,
so it has kind of geopolitical power.
It has,
um,
you know,
population, as you said,
with cultural prestige.
And of course the great symbol of this cultural prestige is the place where,
uh,
Mary Antoinette has gone and where she will spend much of her life,
which is the enormous palace of Versailles.
It's where they're married.
This enormous palace kind of 700 rooms,
uh,
2000 windows,
the roofs cover a hundred hectares.
I mean,
on an enormous scale.
And it's basically the physical embodiment of,
of.
Of the style of government that the French monarchy represents,
which is a kind of monarchical absolutism.
Yeah.
Um,
I mean,
the French monarchy had always been powerful,
but since the,
the 16th and then through the 17th and definitely into the 18th century,
it's,
it's become more and more it's monopolized power more and more.
And the figure who represents that is the great grandfather of Louis the 15th and predecessor,
Louis the 14th,
who had basically annihilated the nobility as an independent political class.
He had required them to come to Versailles and they are merely planets orbiting the sun.
Yeah.
Sun King,
the sun King.
And so Versailles sets fashion manners dress everything for the whole of Europe.
So the great rival of Louis the 14th,
the Duke of Marlborough,
when he,
you know,
he,
he celebrates his victories over the Louis the 14th by building a kind of ersatz Versailles.
Yeah.
Blenheim palace.
Blenheim palace for Marianne Trinette and indeed pretty much for everybody.
I mean,
it's a very oppressive place,
isn't it?
Oh,
it's,
it's awful because the court is,
so she's grown up in the Habsburg court,
which is much more informal and is becoming more informal during her childhood.
But the French court is governed by,
I mean,
it's,
it's partly because it's governed by these very,
very strict ceremonial hierarchical rules,
but also it is a kind of snake pit of politics,
isn't it?
With people jostling for power the whole time.
Yes.
And one of the problems for Marianne Trinette is that her patron,
the Duke de Choiseul falls from power only a few months after her marriage.
And he,
you know,
he'd been her sponsor,
her protector.
And that means that she's just a very young girl,
teenager,
and she's surrounded by people who hate her and hate Austria.
So the aunts of the Dauphin,
so Louis the 15th's daughters,
they hate Austria.
Also,
the Dauphin has younger brothers.
And one in particular,
the Comte de Provence,
who in due course,
vastly in the future,
and I use the word vastly advisedly,
will become Louis the 18th.
I mean,
a man of colossal size.
But at this point,
he's just,
you know,
he's still very young.
He's just a teenager himself,
but he's consumed with resentment of the fact that he's not going to be king.
So he's,
he's a potential snake.
A younger brother who turns out to be a snake.
Who could ever,
that will never happen in monarchical history again,
will it Tom?
Never again.
Yeah.
There are certain parallels to contemporary royals that we'll be teasing out over the course of this series,
I think.
And poor Marie Antoinette feels completely cut off.
And she complains that,
you know,
all her correspondence is being looked at,
that nowhere that she locks anything is safe.
And essentially,
this is,
I mean,
this is the kind of treatment that all foreign queens in Versailles are put through.
They are kind of there as hostages,
as much as anything else.
And,
you know,
they're not expected to have a good time.
You know,
they're not expected to enjoy themselves.
But Marie Antoinette is,
she's strong enough.
And right from the beginning,
it's clear that she's a much stronger character than her husband.
And it's clear that she is,
when she gets,
you know,
when she becomes queen,
she is going to kick back against this kind of formality.
So there's a kind of classic moment where,
for some reason,
she's riding on a donkey.
It's the kind of thing,
I guess,
that,
you know,
a teenage girl might enjoy doing,
but that the comtester really disapproves of.
So she falls off the donkey and she kind of makes this witty quip that she'd better send
to the comtester to find out what the etiquette is for a dauphine falling off a donkey.
And you can see there that this is an attitude that is going to rub up against a lot that
has made Versailles tick.
Yeah.
However,
having said that,
that she's resentful of the kind of the formality and the stiffness of it all,
there is also the fact that Versailles,
particularly under Louis XV,
is a kind of,
it's a showcase for unsettling displays of royal libertinism because Louis XV,
although personally quite a kind of modest and shy person,
I mean,
he's a bit of a dirty old man as well.
A bit.
At some,
he's just,
he only ever,
I mean,
from morning till night,
he only ever thinks about one thing.
Is it not true that the first thing he said when he was told about Marie Antoinette's
existence,
you know,
when he was...
No,
it's when she's arrived.
Oh, right.
When she's arrived.
And the first thing he says is,
does she have large breasts?
I mean,
that is,
that's bad form.
And he's disappointed to learn that she doesn't.
From your father-in-law,
you don't want to hear it,
do you?
No.
And particularly,
because he keeps,
you know,
he's been a great man for mistresses.
So he's,
he had a very celebrated mistress,
Madame du Pompadour,
but she's gone.
And the new mistress,
the Comtesse du Barry,
who's been elevated to that title,
she's a kind of former courtesan.
And she has,
it's almost,
I mean,
it's a kind of semi-formal title,
the Maîtresse en titre.
But Marie Antoinette is appalled by this.
You know,
she's been raised as a devout Catholic.
Yeah.
There's nothing like this in Vienna.
And so she,
she defies court protocol by refusing to even speak to the Comtesse du Barry.
And Marie Theresa,
her mother is furious about this because she's trying to get France to back her in a kind
of dispute over a chunk of Poland.
Yeah.
And she says,
look,
you've got to talk to Madame du Barry.
You know,
I need you to do this.
So,
Marie Antoinette does eventually.
And she says to,
to,
to Madame du Barry,
there are many people at Versailles today.
And there's great cheering.
Hurrah!
Finally,
the dam is broken.
Yeah.
She never says anything else.
Okay.
But fortunately for Marie Antoinette,
neither Madame du Barry,
nor Louis XV,
are long for the world because on the 27th of April,
1774,
Louis XV falls ill.
And gossip will say that he falls ill.
And in Italian,
the word gossip,
it's a very predictable way because Madame du Barry has supposedly sourced a young peasant
girl for him.
And the valet has brought this peasant girl in and the peasant girl turns out to have
had smallpox.
And so he,
he,
his whole face ends up a great super rating mass of a bronze mask enlarged by the crust.
Oh my word.
That's nice.
So,
so that,
that thing that you just said there,
gossip has it or rumor has it.
That's really,
really important because this is an age where the,
the court is kind of hermetically sealed off from Paris and from,
and therefore from the rest of France.
And so most people learn about the king and queen through rumor and gossip.
And this is an age when people are,
there are pamphlets,
people are swap in ballads.
People are,
you know,
there's,
it's a very literate,
very news friendly society in a way that has not really existed before.
And Dominic,
what is more is that,
that you say that it's so important,
that Versailles is hermetically sealed.
I mean,
it kind of is in one way,
but in another way,
it isn't because all the different factions in Versailles are leaking stuff.
So all the,
the kind of the,
the,
the scandalous stories that are told about the queen and in due course about Marie Antoinette,
you know,
these are not coming from disgruntled Republicans.
They're coming from power players at the very heart of the court,
often from the royal family itself.
Yeah.
So,
I mean,
this,
the,
the wellspring of all the gossip and slander that will overwhelm Marie Antoinette in the period of the revolution has been established by,
by Versailles itself.
Anyway,
so,
so whether he's,
whether Louis XV is,
is dying because he's been brought,
you know,
a peasant girl by his mistress or not is up for grabs.
But what,
what is clear is that on the 10th of May,
1774,
he dies.
The news is brought to the Dauphin and there's kind of amazing descriptions of how the,
the,
the sound of the news being brought to him and of people running to come and tell him is like a kind of swelling tidal wave.
Power has left.
The king is dead.
Long live the king.
And the Dauphin is with Marie Antoinette.
Of course,
he's no longer the Dauphin.
He's now Louis XVI.
And there are various accounts of what they say when they're told the news.
But the most celebrated one is that they fall to their knees and cry out,
may God guide and protect us for we are too young to reign.
Because they were 18 and 19,
something like that.
Yeah.
And I think they're aware that France faces massive problems.
But Marie Antoinette later writes to Maria Theresa,
her mother,
and says,
I cannot refrain from admiring the workings of Providence,
which has chosen me,
the youngest of your children to occupy the finest throne in Europe.
But the question is,
Dominic,
what will she do with that power?
Anyone could see that Marie Antoinette would dominate the new king.
So says John Hardman and his book,
Marie Antoinette,
The Making of a French Queen.
Now,
that idea that Louis XVI,
who,
of course,
is a very ill-fated king,
because as most of our listeners will know,
he ends up having an appointment with the guillotine.
Is it fair to say,
Tom,
that he is merely her puppet?
He is a weaker man,
isn't he,
than the Marie Antoinette?
And they,
well,
let's talk about their relationship a bit.
So do they get on?
Are they a happy couple,
would you say?
There are significant incompatibilities.
I think it's fair to say.
So we could just go through some of them.
So one is attitudes to music.
Okay.
So Marie Antoinette is very,
very musical.
She can play the harp.
She can play the harpsichord.
She can play the flute.
Her brother,
Joseph II,
who is ruling along with Maria Theresa,
his mother,
is the great patron of Mozart.
Marie Antoinette had met Mozart when they were six years old.
Imagine meeting Mozart and you're the same age.
You'd feel so inadequate,
wouldn't you?
Yeah.
And,
so she is very,
very musical.
Louis XVI is notoriously hostile to the arts and to music in particular.
And this becomes,
again,
becomes the kind of topic of gossip.
So in the pamphlets,
it's kind of,
you know,
people laugh at him for his lack of musicality.
He's like a British culture secretary.
He is.
Yes,
he is.
No knowledge of the arts or interest in any of the music or anything like that.
Yeah.
He might once have seen Star Wars,
but that would be the limit of his cultural engagement.
Yeah.
So that's pretty much where he is.
And then,
of course,
we mentioned the dog that Marie Antoinette was not allowed to bring into France because
it was,
it was an Austrian dog.
This dog was called Mops and it was a pug.
She was absolutely,
this is,
I think is basically what makes her burst into tears and fall onto the,
the bosom of the Comtesse de Neuilly.
Yeah.
Is being deprived of the dog.
But listeners will be glad and relieved to know that she does in due course get reunited
with Mops.
So that's,
that's,
that's happy.
Louis hates dogs.
And more particularly,
I'm sad to say,
as a cat owner.
Yeah.
He hates cats.
He's right.
He's right in that regard,
but hating dogs is madness.
No,
he's not.
He's absolutely not.
Cats are rubbish.
Because he takes it,
he takes it to an unacceptable degree,
which is,
so as Dauphin,
his favourite activity was to,
was to shoot cats on the.
Love it.
On the roofs of Versailles.
So he's basically,
he's,
he's shooting strays.
Yeah.
This apparently is acceptable for sport in Versailles.
But he accidentally shoots the Angora cat of the Comtesse de Maurepoix.
And when he does this,
he's actually very upset and he apologises profusely.
It's a story that does kind of,
I think sum up an aspect of his character,
which is that on one level he's very heedless of the suffering,
whether of cats or of people out in the,
in the fields of La France Profonde.
But on,
on another level,
when he's informed of kind of individual examples of suffering,
he's very upset about it and worried about it.
I think you're too harsh though,
saying he's heedless of,
I don't think he's any more heedless than anybody else sealed off in the palace of Versailles
would be from.
Right.
But I think if you're shooting stray cats,
I mean,
you just assume this is the kind of thing that a king does or,
you know,
it's acceptable sport,
but when he,
when it's brought home to him,
what the implications are,
then he worries about it.
And I think you could say the same about his relationship to the broader troubles out in
France,
that he's not aware of it.
He's not aware of it until he's,
he's informed about it and then he doesn't really know what to do.
Yeah.
He's not,
he's not casual about it,
but he,
he,
he's,
he might perhaps slightly oblivious to it.
Now he's a very,
his big thing is hunting,
isn't it?
We've had two tremendous huntsmen on the rest of history recently,
Franz Ferdinand and the Kaiser.
And,
and Custer.
And Custer,
well three.
And actually Louis,
that would be a brilliant hunting party with those,
those four men,
because Louis the 16th is a tremendous huntsman.
He absolutely adores it.
And he keeps a journal where he writes down how many,
how many animals he's killed.
So the famous thing that everybody says on the day of the fall of the Bastille in 1789,
that he wrote in his journal,
rien,
as in nothing happened today.
That's rubbish.
Actually,
the nothing was because he hadn't killed any animals that day.
So very disappointing day.
I mean,
I think it's also fair to say that he's not a great diarist.
So on the day he meets Marie Antoinette,
he says,
met mademoiselle la Dauphine and the day his mother dies,
my mother died.
Okay.
Like Camus l'étranger,
my mother died today or yesterday.
I don't remember.
It's obviously a French tradition.
Yeah.
So he's not,
he's not a,
he's not a great diarist.
And he,
as you said,
he is a great huntsman,
but I think the,
one of the reasons why he adores it so much is that he's very good at it.
So he's,
you know,
he's a very good horseman,
but when he's on his own two feet,
he's incredibly kind of maladroit,
um,
and,
and socially as well as physically.
So he hates dancing.
He's,
he's not good at kind of chit chat.
He's not good at the kind of,
you know,
all the stuff that people at Versailles get.
I,
I doing,
he doesn't really like it.
And,
and basically he has the soul of a naval engineer.
Yeah.
So he,
he loves fleets.
He loves harbors.
Um,
and he loves tinkering with locks.
You know,
he has his own workshop.
Oh,
I love this stuff.
Simon Sharma is brilliant on this.
So he's got this study,
hasn't he?
With all these maps and nautical instruments.
And he will just sit there with a lock,
like messing around,
you know,
surrounded by all this stuff.
He's like an,
a tinkering inventor.
And actually,
I think that comes over as quite endearing.
Yeah.
So Sharma writes,
the struggle to make the perfect lock.
So this is something that Louis XVI is doing was a symbol of sublime
aptness for the monarch who repeatedly failed to make things turn as he wished.
But in his appartement privé,
he moved silently in his plain frock coat amidst polished lenses,
armillary spheres,
burnished brass and orries with all the freedom and power of omegas.
Oh,
I love that.
I mean,
let me just say one thing right at the outset.
Um,
for those people who haven't read it,
or have maybe heard about it and just can't be bothered to read it because it's quite
long.
Simon Sharma's book Citizens,
um,
is insanely enjoyable.
It's just,
it's just,
I mean,
I know it's,
it's always tempting to be revisionist and to say of a great historian and a great book,
ah,
it's actually rubbish.
It is,
it is tip top.
It is brilliant.
Every page.
And has great pictures as well.
It does.
So,
so Marie Antoinette would have enjoyed that.
She would,
she would have looked at the pictures.
That's nice.
Yeah.
Um,
but,
but Dominic,
just to say that there is an alternative perspective on this,
which is the perspective of,
of,
um,
pamphleteers,
one of whom describes him as a zombie who spends his time making locks and bolts.
And you may wonder,
well,
where is this tone coming from?
Well,
I,
I think it's coming from the Prince Harry of Versailles,
who is the Comte de Provence.
Right.
Who is consumed with envy and spleen.
he is feeding all kinds of kind of hostile material out to the pamphleteers.
But I think it also reflects the fact that the ultimate incompatibility,
it seems certainly in the early years of the marriage is sexual.
And if there's one thing that a French King is supposed to do,
it's to be sexually voracious.
So it is better to be Louis the 15th,
you know,
an absolute goat.
Who was this bloke's grandfather,
by the way,
just to clarify.
Yeah.
Uh,
than,
than to be,
uh,
sexually,
incompetent,
which is clearly what Louis the 16th is.
And it,
it takes them seven years to consummate the marriage.
And there's much,
there was much debate at the time.
And there was much debate to this day about what the problem was.
So,
uh,
a favorite thesis is that Louis the 16th suffered from a condition called
phimosis,
which basically means that the,
um,
the foreskin covers the head of the penis,
which means that it's very difficult to,
uh,
erections become very painful.
Um,
I,
I think the consensus now,
I gather,
I don't quite know how they've arrived at this consensus is that this isn't the case.
Theo has written in the chat.
Thanks,
Tom.
And I'm sure many of the listeners are also very grateful to you for,
uh,
for that very,
that real,
that,
that slightly unnecessary detail.
It's not unnecessary because actually the,
the,
the question of why the king and queen are not having children is a matter of,
of,
of profound state.
And,
and I think discussed Tom,
but at the highest level.
So absolutely.
Joseph,
the lowest level.
So Joseph the second,
who is the emperor of Austria and his Mary Antoinette's,
uh,
brother,
she must've told him about it because he writes to another brother and says,
I mean,
I,
I'm not going to go into all the gory details,
but he basically says they do.
They do try to have marital relations.
Um,
Louis state,
and I quote,
stays there without moving for perhaps two minutes.
And then,
um,
says,
good night,
you know,
withdraws.
Yes.
And says,
yeah,
I was,
I was omitting that detail because I thought,
yeah,
I'm not as keen on the,
uh,
but anyway,
he says,
good night.
Thank you very much.
All good.
And,
um,
they're not actually completing the necessary act.
And basically they need doctors or courtiers or whoever to explain to them.
Well,
according to tradition,
actually that comment,
you know,
Joseph the second makes that report after he's been on a trip to Versailles.
And he's spoken to both the king and the queen.
And,
and the,
the,
the tradition is,
is that he explains what needs to be done to Louis the 16th with reference to a lock
and a key.
Right.
You know,
as a,
he would enjoy the lock analogy.
I just find the whole thing very,
slightly implausible,
but anyway,
there's no question that this makes him a kind of object of,
of,
of some contempt,
um,
which,
which in many ways is unfair because I think you're right.
You know,
I,
he is dutiful.
He is hardworking.
He is conscientious.
He does develop a reputation for,
for kindness.
Uh,
maybe cats accepted,
but there is this sense that he is,
I don't know.
He's a bit of a,
so,
so Chantal Thomas writes for a sovereign,
the line between goodness and imbecility was easily crossed.
And I think that Louis the 16th is on that line that people can admire him as a respect
him as a good man while simultaneously despising him as someone who is incompetent or useless
as a sovereign.
He's not an impressive man.
He's not a character.
He's not a charismatic or formidable man.
He doesn't inspire respect.
He's a,
probably quite a nice man,
but a weak man.
Is that fair,
Tom?
I think probably.
Yes.
I think he's,
it's felt that he is,
he is not of Royal material really.
But having said that,
uh,
whether it's Joseph the second or not,
who managed to explain to him what he's got to do,
they do finally get together.
And,
uh,
Mary Antoinette gives Louis four children,
including crucially two sons.
So a Dauphin and a spare.
And,
um,
and they end up quite a devoted couple.
Um,
so he does not amazing.
He doesn't take a mistress.
So on one level,
that of course only enhances the idea of him that he's,
you know,
he's not,
he's not a kind of the Liberty.
He's not an alpha male.
Um,
but on another,
he's kind of upholding an almost bourgeois standard of kind of marital fidelity.
He banishes Madame du Barry who gets packed off.
Um,
and Madame du Barry,
like Madame du Pompadour before her,
um,
had been,
had,
uh,
had this splendid kind of grace and favor residents in the grounds of Versailles,
kind of little Chateau called the Petit Trianon.
And Louis gives this to,
uh,
to Mary Antoinette.
So now it's the Queens and she absolutely loves it because,
you know,
we've talked about how resentful and hostile she is to the kind of stifling etiquette of
Versailles.
The Petit Trianon offers her a bolt hole and it gives her the perfect opportunity.
To vent all her,
you know,
qualities of spontaneity and simplicity and impulse that she loves.
So on that,
um,
you were saying about her,
not reading a book.
Simon Sharma says in Citizens,
like all adolescent girls of her generation,
she drank deep at the well of sentimental literature.
Her library was full of Samuel Richardson,
Rousseau,
Mercier,
Restive de Breton,
et cetera.
Now her library was full of them.
Maybe she didn't necessarily read them,
but as Sharma says,
she,
um,
is steeped in the culture that is the most modern,
fashionable,
forward-looking culture.
She's not stuck in the mud.
She's not a relic of the Ancien Regime.
She's interested,
particularly in the stuff that people associate with the philosopher,
the thinker Rousseau,
which are virtue,
simplicity,
nature,
um,
a sort of,
uh,
as you said,
spontaneity and a kind of,
yeah.
And these are all qualities that will come to be seen in due course,
as features of the revolution.
But Marie Antoinette is a massive enthusiast for them.
So much so that amazingly in 1782,
she goes and visits Rousseau's grave outside Paris.
So she's a kind of,
uh,
a,
a.
I don't know.
I think she's perfectly possible to kind of,
she's probably skimmed through it.
Yeah.
Or being told,
I,
I think that's perfectly possible too,
by the way,
I think it's,
I mean,
that's how most people actually pick up fashionable ideas,
they pick these days that you pick them up on,
on Facebook or in conversation,
but you won't necessarily read the wellspring.
Yeah,
and she is for that reason,
very,
very fashionable,
fashionable because her lack of enthusiasm for fashion as prescribed by Versailles
is itself becomes the fashion. And the enthusiasm for Rousseau, the idea that one should lead a
simple unadorned life and that this is the key to virtue. At the Petit Trianon, the emphasis
is on hiding the presence of servants. So in Versailles, it's all about having as many
servants as possible. Every time Marie Antoinette gets dressed, hundreds of maids surround her to
do it. In the Petit Trianon, it's different. And kind of famously, she commissions a landscape
architect to design her an amouristique, a kind of a rustic hamlet, a rustic village
that has cats.
Towers with ribbons on, alpine sheep, a watermill. And this, of course, becomes notorious because
it's the idea of a queen pretending to be a shepherdess that strikes up all kinds of
unfortunate resonances. But she is the embodiment of fashion.
But only notorious because the revolution happens. I mean, had France's finances been
in better shape and there's no revolution.
People would be charmed by this.
Yeah. Well, people would say it's an entertaining quirk of 18th century, you know,
monarchical life. They wouldn't think anything of it.
Yeah. And far from saying that the poor should eat cake, she's very worried about
the poor. The poor as kind of represented by photogenic paupers who can be given charity
by her.
She's the Angelina Jolie of the 18th century, Tom.
So 1785, she lodges and feeds 12 poor families at the Petit Trianon.
But there's a quality of the fact that she's very, I think she's very impressed by the
sense she has of her own virtue and she wants people to know about it while simultaneously
genuinely being worried about it.
I mean, all of those things can be true.
And she wants to make sure that her children are raised in this.
She's a very, very good mother, a very attentive mother.
So 1784, the year before that, it had been a terrible winter.
And she provides her children with what one of her companions describes as a lesson in
doing good.
By bringing in a great kind of partnership.
A style of Toyr.
And then saying, you can't have these because we're going to sell these toys and use them
to get blankets and bread among children in need.
That's very, that's, that's, that, that's quite surprising.
Yeah.
Very Dickensian.
As well.
So Chantal Thomas describes, this wonderfully she's she was fond of Charity and never tired
of the spectacle of her own goodness.
So I think again, she is the precursor of a kind of modern type of celebrity, kind of
Celebrity Charity.
a duchess of sussex tom yes well yeah a slight quality there um so so that's on the kind of the
moral level but she also creates this kind of new kind of fashion that that is is absolutely
repudiating the kind of the stiff formality of versailles so she she has this dressmaker
who shockingly is allowed ready access to her apartments yeah you know she doesn't go through
all the the court protocols that normally restricts people who can see the queen and
basically marie antoinette is kind of discarding all the the rich silks of the court for flowing
white muslins um for kind of simple costumes fresh flowers kind of bucolic adornments right
and not only that she's not wearing she stopped she stops wearing corsets and stays and all those
things that kind of really button you up it's all it's very again it's very
rousseau go back to nature it's going back to nature i mean shama says you can see the natural
line of you can actually see what her body looks like under the dress which of course is not the
case with the incredibly rigid and structured dresses that people are wearing 10 or 20 well
it's not they're wearing them earlier they're wearing them at the same time but she is breaking
with the rules of a french kind of hierarchical dress absolutely and there's there's a sense that
you know i said that she marie antoinette in a way invents
modern fashion uh and she does that because she is you know she whatever the french say she is
the queen of france so she in a sense is the most for that reason she has the highest profile of
any woman in europe um but also because um she she's a genius at it and the idea of waking up
every morning and just deciding what you want to wear you know what clothes you're going to have
uh how you're going to do your hair rather than having it prescribed according to rigid structures
is something revolutionary and it's that you know literally revolutionary because this is the style
of fashion that will come in during the french revolution and marie antoinette to that extent
i think is it's the godmother of france's modern reputation as the home of fashion and it's you
know and it's not and we've talked about clothes there is also hair so there's an absolutely
wonderful book uh with the great title marie antoinette's head by uh will bashaw which is about
hairdresser who is a man called monsieur leonard who will feature throughout the story right um and
again this is very very shocking that this he's a male hairdresser so not female you know not ladies
maid he's a celebrity hairdresser and he like uh like madame bertin has ready access to her
so there's something very very diva about this i mean it's absolutely recognizable and he
gives her a whole succession of kind of unbelievably grandiose hairstyles so um they're
called uh that the hairstyle that that marie antoinette is is initially promoting is called
le pouf sentimental which is such a you know these are the ones that people will immediately
my hair is kind of the sentimental poof i mean that's a hard sentence to carry off right
it's it's kind of t you know that you can imagine they're kind of teased up um gauze and plumes and
very very risky because you know there are candles in the chandeliers so if you brush against it you
might just go up in up in flames and there are various kind of styles so you have the the erison
which is unpowdered hair so that's kind of you know going back to nature there slight hint of
going back to nature and they're kind of curled to the tips and rising in tears so it looks like
an erison a hedgehog there's the zephyr which is flowers woven into the hair so again there's
different types of hair styles and indeed we shall talk about this in a snack let's take
it one more time but in 1781 m Hinna is summoned by marianheart that's how i call it
polarized law of choicedie queen of justiceiedo
and um and well if we go right through that so so very very short we've got two of these
two about jest and like most kings and queens he's got Bossio and porcelain Такo there's like that
one that would befold investiction made about not overview of the many census as well as a culture세요
Ayala7
and then in 1781 Messiah LenaEina is summoned by monitoring status distraught because she
And it creates this fashion for natural hairstyles that spreads across Versailles, spreads across Paris, spreads across France, spreads across Europe.
And she has people who are around her, doesn't she?
She has, you use the expression, her squad, which may sound like Taylor Swift.
But she does have this coterie of very, very close friends who will later become, like her, controversial, some of whom, frankly, are doomed to incredibly tragic and blood-curdling ends.
Yes.
I mean, they, so there are two in particular.
There's the Duchess de Polignac, who, I mean, is very, very beautiful, exquisite manners, absolutely adores kind of gossip and intrigue.
So I think, I think.
I think it's kind of less Taylor Swift.
It's more, it's more the plastics in Mean Girls, which I know you haven't seen, but which I, as a parent of two daughters, have seen a lot.
Brilliant, brilliant film.
And I think that anyone who's seen that film, if you think of Marie Antoinette and the Duchess de Polignac as the plastics, who are the kind of the queen bees in a high school.
And then there's, there's another, the plastic, there's this sidekick who's always trying to make fetch.
Happen the word fetch, and she never does.
And I think that that, that character would be the process de lumbar, who is very, very vapid.
She's always, she, so it's the kind of brilliantly bitchy account of her by the Comtesse de Gemli.
She never had an opinion of her own in conversation.
She always adopted the opinion of the person who passed for the wittiest in a way that was utterly unique.
Whenever there was a serious discussion, she never spoke pretending to fall into a trance.
Then she would suddenly appear to snap out of her reverie and repeat word for word.
As though it came from her, what the person whose opinion she had decided to adopt had just said.
She affected great surprise when told someone had just said the same thing.
She assured everyone she hadn't heard of it.
So I think you get there a sense that this is not, you know, they, Marie Antoinette likes these people precisely because they are not witty.
They are not brilliant.
She can enjoy their company.
Inevitably, gossip will say that they're all lesbians, that they're all engaging in sapphic rights.
Mm.
Um, the, the, the Duchess.
De Polignac in particular, who, who becomes widely, widely hated, but they, but both of them are, are, are, are strongly disliked.
There are also male guests going to the Petit Trianon of whom the most notorious is a dashing Swedish officer called Axel von Fersen, um, who is the son of a field marshal and who had met Marie Antoinette at a masked ball at the opera in 1774 when she was still the Dauphin, when she was still the Dauphine.
And he hadn't recognized her, which is obviously a kind of great.
A real for, for, for Marie Antoinette from that point on the regular visits, the two indisputably become close.
Again, it is taken for granted that they are sleeping.
I think this is most unlikely because it's not really in her character.
It's not her style.
Yeah, no.
And it would be mad for her to do that.
Um, but there is clearly a kind of heedlessness about this.
Uh, I mean, to have these kind of very close, intimate relationships and to, to kind of, um, thumb her nose at.
The formalities and the hierarchies of Versailles to bring down everything that the Comtesse de Neuilly had represented.
I mean, she's, she's building up trouble for herself.
There's an amazing quotation actually from her brother, Joseph II, who wrote to his brother, to their brother, Leopold.
And he said, she has no etiquette.
She goes out and runs around alone or with a few people without the outward signs of her position.
She looks a little improper and while this would be all right for a private person, she is not doing.
Her.
Her job.
And that is the issue, isn't it?
That she's not playing the part of a French queen as the French people expect.
No, she's not.
And I think what is more and even more damaging for her is that she's actually playing the part of a mistress because the petty Trianon is where the mistress lives and Queens are not supposed to live like Mitch's mistresses.
And so over the course of Louis, the 16th reign going into the 1780s.
She is, um, she's coming to be hated as Queens often are hated as kind of, you know, the embodiment of, of, of Royal arrogance and of kind of absolutism.
But she's also being hated as favorites are.
She's been cast as a kind of a, a voracious, greedy blood sucking nymphomaniac.
Yeah.
And the pair of these images are kind of being fused because.
A mistress is always being accused of extravagance.
Yeah.
I mean, that's, that's, that's what they're there to do that, that, you know, that, and kind of amazingly story start to be repeated that Mary Antoinette is literally maintaining at the expense of the state, a whole tank full of leeches, which is a kind of horrible idea, a sort of metaphor.
And also of course, mistresses are sexually promiscuous.
And so this is why the stories that she's having, you know.
You know, sapphic affairs and sleeping with, um, you know, Swedish officers and things like that.
It's why they, they have such currency.
And the interesting thing about that, Tom, is that they start, I think it's Robert's answer makes this point that they start in 1774, so 15 years before the revolution.
And when she's still only 18, 19 years old, so very early on these stories that she has this kind of voracious sexual appetite that her lock obsessed husband is not satisfying.
And that, you know, there's this kind of extravagance and depravity sucking the energy and the money out of France.
They start very early, don't they?
And she's never able to shake them.
Right.
And I, and to, to reiterate, because I think this is so important, these stories are not coming from Republican, um, people who, who, who hate the monarchy.
It's coming from her rivals at the court.
These are the people who are spreading it.
And it reflects a culture.
Among the nobility and it, it, it reflects, uh, I think, uh, a character of libertinism that you get at the court that Louis the 15th had exemplified and which you get in, in, um, the clothes, great novel, uh, dangerous liaisons translated the film people who've seen the film.
I mean, the whole thing is about debauching people, the, the idea that the aristocracy are cruel and sexually predatory.
And of course the, the writer who absolutely exemplifies this is the Marquis de Sade, who we did it.
An episode on, and there's a sense in which the Marquis de Sade is, is reworking ideas that are very, very current in pornography at the time.
And Marie Antoinette, who had refused to speak to Madame du Barry, because, you know, she'd been a courtesan who had been so unsexually voracious that she, you know, the marriage hadn't been consummated for seven years.
She comes to be the kind of the, the protagonist of.
This is almost coincidental for some reasons.
Um, the wrapper of the começa night's, uh, violence that pickers sweet waterproof dish programa.
My dear international listeners, you may be wondering what the Pascoe wanted to lecture us about is, but it's very stuck.
Peter any article about it about the
Well, this talk, whether anyone has seen it, but I've, it's so quick.
The, the, um, type of fiction is.
they lack an obvious focus they are underground they are being percolated by kind of court
rivalries but then in 1784 there's an absolute catastrophe because marie antoinette finds
herself engulfed in a complete firestorm of scandal and actually dominic it's not just a
scandal it's an affair the affair of the diamond necklace and tom what an amazing story this is
thank you so much for that i think there's only one expressions given that we are in 18th century
france that was a genuine tour de force and on that bombshell uh au revoir everybody adama